<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<pretext xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:lang="en-US">

  <xi:include href="./bookinfo.xml"/>

  <book xml:id="discrete-class-notes">
    <title>Math 321 Class Notes</title>
    <frontmatter xml:id="front-matter">
      <titlepage>
        <author>
          <personname>John Hammond</personname>
          <email>hammond@math.wichita.edu</email>
          <department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
          <institution>Wichita State University</institution>
        </author>
      </titlepage>

      <colophon>
        <copyright>
          <holder>John Hammond</holder>
          <year>2018-2019</year>
          <minilicense>Creative Commons BY-SA</minilicense>
        </copyright>
        <website>
          <name>Class Notes Website</name>
          <address>http://www.math.wichita.edu/discrete-book</address>
        </website>
      </colophon>
      <preface>
        <p>
          The WSU Catalog says of this course: 
          <blockquote>
            <p>
              MATH 321.  Discrete Structures I
            </p>
            <p>
              Cross-listed as CS 321. Provides a mathematical foundation essential to the entire computer science curriculum. Includes propositional and predicate logic, induction, recursion and counting techniques. Prerequisite: MATH 242 or equivalent with a grade point of 2.000 or better.
            </p>
          </blockquote>
        </p>

        <p>
          We'll be exploring these areas, along with enough number theory to do an interesting application to encryption. 
        </p>
        <p>
          This course is very different that your past math courses. Keep an open mind, and please ask questions! This might be the <q>hardest</q> math class you take, but it can also be one of the most rewarding.
        </p>
      </preface>

      <acknowledgement>
        <p>
          This book borrows heavily from the exercises of Oscar Levin's <url href="https://github.com/oscarlevin/discrete-book">Discrete Mathematics: An Open Introduction</url>.
        </p>
        <p>
          The material in section <xref ref="section-counting-fib"/> was first discovered in Arthur Benjamin and Jennifer Quinn's <pubtitle>Proofs that Really Count: The Art of Combinatorial Proof</pubtitle>, and the exercises in that section come from that book, and influenced every choice of Fibonacci sequence problem in the remainder of the text.
        </p>
        <p>
          Special thanks goes to the Wichita State Open/Alternative Textbook Initiative for their generous grant to help expand the text.
        </p>
        <p>
          I'm also grateful for you, reader, as we go on this journey of mathematics together. This is going to be fun.
        </p>
      </acknowledgement>
    </frontmatter>


    <xi:include href="./ch_basics.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./ch_logic.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./ch_numtheory.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./ch_sequences.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./ch_counting.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="./ch_appendix.xml"/>


</book>
</pretext>
