<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- I think this should be included with the logic props section, not on its own. //-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="section-prop-apps">
  <title>Applications of Propositional Logic</title>

  <subsection>
    <title> Translating English Sentences</title>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Decompose each part of the statement into individual propositional variables and write as a compound proposition:
          <ol>
            <li> You drink coffee only if you put the ground coffee into the maker and don't forget to press brew. </li>
            <li> TODO </li>
          </ol>
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p> Answering the coffee question, we let: 
        <ul>
          <li><m>d</m>: You can drink coffee.</li>
          <li><m>g</m>: You put ground coffee into the maker</li>
          <li><m>f</m>: You forgot to press brew.</li>
        </ul>
        Then the statement is <m>d \to (g \wedge \neg f)</m>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Boolean Searches</title>
    <p>
      Search engines using Boolean searches use logical connectives. 
      <ul>
        <li> AND requires records match both terms </li>
        <li> OR returns records that match one or both of the terms </li>
        <li> NOT (or sometimes AND NOT) excludes a term </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      For example, if I wanted to search the WSU library catalog to learn about Georg Cantor's diagonalization argument <xref ref="section-objects-sets-diag"/>, but I want to exclude anything about computability, I could do the following search: 
      <image source="images/library-catalog.png"/>

      <note>
        <p>
          Remember that <q>but</q> is a conjunction!
        </p>
      </note>

    </p>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Logic Puzzles</title>
    <p>
      A classic example is that we're on the island of knights and knaves. Knights always tell the truth. Knaves always lie.
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          We encounter two people A and B.
          <ul>
            <li>
              A says: <q>B is a knight.</q>
            </li>
            <li>
              B says: <q>The two of us are opposite types.</q>
            </li>
          </ul>
          What is the conclusion?
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>
    <exercise>
      <statement>
        <p>
          This is a favorite of my daughter. You encounter a guard standing at a fork in the road. It is not known whether the guard will tell the truth or lie. One of the paths leads to great treasure, the other leads to a violent and scary death. You are allowed to ask one and only one question to the guard.
        </p>
        <p>
          What can you ask the guard in order to ensure you go on the path towards the treasure?
        </p>
      </statement>
    </exercise>
  </subsection>
</section>
