<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="section-logic-proofs">
  <title>An introduction to proofs</title>
  
  <definition>
    <ul>
      <li> A <term>theorem</term> is a statement can be shown to be true. (an important statement)
      </li>
      <li>
        A <term>proposition</term> is a "less important" theorem.
      </li>
      <li> The tools we use to prove a theorem are <term>axioms</term> (or <term>postulates</term>) which are basic assumptions we make, as well as other theorems we've already proven.
      </li>
      <li>
        A less important theorem that will be helpful in proving others is called a <term>lemma</term>.
      </li>
      <li>
      A <term>corollary</term> is a theorem that follows directly from a theorem just proved.</li>
      <li>
        A <term>conjecture</term> is a statement that we think my be true (our intuition suggests it)
      </li>
    </ul>
  </definition>

  <example>
    <statement>
      <p>
        "If <m>n</m> is an odd integer, then <m>n^2</m> is odd."
      </p>
      <p>
        This means for the universe of discourse of all integers:
        <m> \forall n ((n </m> is odd <m>) \to (n^2 </m> is odd<m>)))</m>
      </p>
    </statement>
  </example>
  <note>
    <statement>
      The universe of discourse was implied in the general statement above. Mathematical propositions will almost always omit the words "for all."
    </statement>
  </note>

  <subsection>
    <title>Direct Proof</title>

    <p>A direct proof is used when proving a proposition of the form <m>p \to q</m>. The goal is to show <m>q</m> is true when we assume <m>p</m> is true. Here's the model:</p>
    <proof>
      <p> Assume <m>p</m> is true. </p>
      <p> ... use logical equivalences (and/or mathematics) ... </p>
      <p> Therefore <m>q</m> is true.</p>
    </proof>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove that the sum of two odd numbers is even.
      </statement>
    </example>


    <example xml:id="example-neven">
      <statement>
        Prove that if <m>n</m> is even, then <m>n^2</m> is even.
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove that if <m>m+n</m> and <m>n + p</m> are even integers, then <m>m+p</m> is even.
      </statement>
    </example>
    
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Indirect Proofs</title>

    <introduction>
      <p>We still want to show <m>p \to q</m> is true, but perhaps that's difficult to approach directly. There are several different indirect proofs. The most frequent are approaches are proofs by contraposition and proofs by contradication.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsubsection>
      <title>Proof by Contraposition</title>
      <p>. A proof by contraposition is a direct proof of <m>\neg q \to \neg p</m>. Here's the model:</p>
      <proof>
        <p> Assume <m>\neg q</m> is true. </p>
        <p> ... use logical equivalences (and/or mathematics) ... </p>
        <p> Show <m>\neg p</m> is true. Therefore, <m>p \to q</m> is true by contraposition. </p>
      </proof>
      <p>
        Remember that <m>\neg q \to \neg p \equiv p \to q</m>, so this is a valid argument.
      </p>
      <example>
        <statement>
          Show that if <m>n</m> is an integer and <m>n^3 + 5</m> is odd, then <m>n</m> is even.
        </statement>
      </example>
      <example xml:id="example-n2even">
        <statement>
          Prove that if <m>n^2</m> is even, then <m>n</m> is even.
        </statement>
      </example>
    </subsubsection>

    <subsubsection>
      <title>Proof by Contradiction</title>
      <p>A proof by contradiction relies on the fact that <m>\neg (p \wedge \neg q) \equiv (p \to q)</m>. We'll assume both that <m>p</m> is true, and we assume the opposite or <m>q</m> is true. Here's the model:</p>
      <proof>
        <p> Assume <m>p</m> is true, and further assume that <m>\neg q</m> is true</p> 
        <p> ... use logical equivalences (and/or mathematics) ... </p>
        <p> Arrive at a logical contradiction. Some impossibility. Therefore, <m>p \to q</m> is true by contradiction.</p>
      </proof>

      <example>
        <statement>
          Prove that <m>\sqrt{2}</m> is irrational
        </statement>
      </example>

      <!-- <example> -->
      <!--   <title>Proof of the infinitude of primes</title> -->
      <!--   <statement> -->
      <!--     Prove that there are infinitely prime numbers. -->
      <!--   </statement> -->
      <!--   <proof> -->

      <!--   </proof> -->

      <!-- </example> -->
    </subsubsection>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Proofs of equivalence
    </title>

    <p>
      For statements which are "if an only if:" <m>p \iff q</m> we need to prove both <m>p \to q</m> and its converse <m>q \to p</m>.
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove that <m>n</m> is even if and only if <m>n^2</m> is even.
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>We actually did this in the two previous subsections. The <xref ref="example-neven">forward direction</xref> and <xref ref="example-n2even">the converse</xref>.</p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove that <m>n</m> is even if and only if <m>7n+4</m> is even.
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove the following are equivalent:
        <ol>
          <li><m>a\lt b</m></li>
          <li>The average of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> is greater than <m>a</m> </li>
          <li>The average of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> is less than <m>b</m> </li>
        </ol>
      </statement>
    </example>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Proof by cases
    </title>

    <p>
      Split an argument into completely separate pieces. In the example below we have two cases. Either <m>x \ge y</m> or <m>x \lt y</m>:
      <example>
        <statement>
          Show that if <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are real numbers, then:
          <ul>
            <li>
              max(<m>x,y</m>) = <m>\dfrac{x+y + |x-y|)}{2}</m>
            </li>
            <li>
              min(<m>x,y</m>) = <m>\dfrac{x+y - |x-y|)}{2}</m>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </statement>
      </example>
      <note>
        <statement>
          We need to prove each claim separately for each case!
        </statement>
      </note>
    </p>
    <p>
      What if the cases might be the same? Below, we have two cases, either <m>x</m> is odd and <m>y</m> is even, or <m>x</m> is even and <m>y</m> is odd:
      <example>
        <statement>
          Prove that <m>5x + 5y</m> is an odd integer when <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are integers of opposite parity (not both even, not both odd). 
        </statement>
      </example>
    </p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Existence Proofs
    </title>

    <p>
      The claim of an existence theorem is that there is some object that has a property. A <term>constructive proof</term> is one which, during the argumentation, tells the reader specifically how to come up with the object in question. A <term>nonconstructive proof</term> merely confirms the existence of an object, but doesn't give any detail as to how to find it.
    </p>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Prove that either <m>2 \cdot 10^{500} + 15</m> or <m>2 \cdot 10^{500} + 16</m> is not a perfect square. 
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Show that between any two rational numbers is another rational number.
      </statement>
    </example>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Uniqueness proofs
    </title>

    <p>
      The claim of a uniqueness theorem is that there exists an element that has a desired property, and that no other element has this property.
      The outline of our proof is often:
      <ul>
        <li>Prove the existence of <m>x</m>, some element that has the property we want.</li>
        <li>Assume that a second element, <m>y</m> also has that property.</li>
        <li>Conclude that <m>x = y</m> </li>
      </ul>
    </p>


    <example>
      <statement>
        Show that if <m>a, b, c</m> are real numbers, then thare is a unique solution to the algebraic equation <m>ax+b=c</m>.
      </statement>
    </example>

    <example>
      <statement>
        Show that if <m>n</m> is an odd integer, then there exists a unique integer <m>k</m> such that <m>n = (k-2) + (k+3)</m>
      </statement>
    </example>


  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Vacuous and Trivial Proofs</title>
    <definition>
      <p>A <term>vacuous statement</term> is one that is true because the hypothesis is false. You can <q>prove</q> a statement is true immediately.
      <example>
        <statement>
          If I play in the Super Bowl, I will throw the game winning touchdown.
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p>
            Vacuous statements are kind of annoying... since I won't ever play in the Super Bowl, it doesn't matter what the truth value of the touchdown statement is. <m>F\to T \equiv T</m> and <m>F \to F \equiv T</m> just the same.
          </p>
        </solution>
      </example>
      </p>
    </definition>

    <definition>
      
      <p>
        If we know that the conclusion of a statement is true, then the statement has a <term>trivial</term> proof.

        <example>
          <statement>
            Let <m>P(x)</m> be the statement <q>If <m>x\in \mathbb{R}</m> and <m>x \gt 0</m> , then <m>x^2 + 1 \ge 0</m></q>.
          </statement>
          <solution>
            <p>
              Since we know that <m>x^2 \ge 0</m> for any real number, <m>x^2 + 1 \ge x^2 \ge 0</m>. We didn't need the hypothesis <m>x \gt 0</m>. This is a trivial proof.
            </p>
          </solution>

        </example>
      </p>
    </definition>

  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Counterexamples Revisited</title>
    <p>
      <!-- Counterexamples are important in mathematics and reasoning in general. It helps you demonstrate  -->
      Recall in math propositions, the universal quantifier is implied and is usually omitted. 
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        Each of the following statements is false. Find a specific counterexample and explain why.
        <ol>
          <li>If <m>n</m> is a real number, then <m>(n+4)^2 = n^2 + 16</m>.</li>
          <li>Every integer is the sum of the squares of two integers.</li>
          <li><m>\forall x \forall y (x^2 = y^2 \to x = y)</m> where the domain of all variables is the set of all integers. </li>
          <li>The product of two irrational numbers is irrational.</li>
          <li>The sum of two irrational numbers is irrational.</li>
        </ol>
      </statement>
    </example>

  </subsection>



</section>
