<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec_relationsfunctions">
  <title> Relations and Functions </title>

  <definition>
    <statement>
      <p>
        Let <m>A \and B</m> be any two sets. A mathematical <term>relation between the sets <m>A</m> and <m>B</m></term> is a collection of ordered pairs from the two sets. That is, if <m>R</m> is a relation of <m>A</m> to <m>B</m>, then <m>R = \{ (a,b) \mid a\in A \and b\in B\}</m>
      </p>
      <p>
        Written another way, <m>R \subseteq A \times B</m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        If <m>a</m> is related to <m>b</m> we will write <m>a R b</m> or <m>(a,b) \in R</m>. If two elements <m>c </m> and <m>d</m> are not related, we write <m>c \not R d</m>.
      </p>
    </statement>
  </definition>

  <example>
    <statement>
      <p>
        If we consider <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> to both be the set of people in your family, and let <m>R</m> be the relation <q><m>a</m> is a sibling of <m>b</m>.</q> Here's an example of my family. Note that, for example, John <m>R</m> Sarah and Sarah<m>R</m> John because she's my sibling, and I'm her sibling. What are the ordered pairs that make up the relation? Which representation do you like better? Why?
      </p>
			<image xml:id="my-family-graph">
				<latex-image>
					\begin{tikzpicture}
	\coordinate (A)  at (0,3);
	\node at (A) [left]{Set $A$};
	\coordinate (B)  at (0,2);
	\node at (B) [left]{John};
	\coordinate (C)  at (0,1);
	\node at (C) [left]{Eric};
	\coordinate (D)  at (0,0);
	\node at (D) [left]{Sarah};

	\coordinate (E)  at (2,3);
	\coordinate (F)  at (2,2);
	\coordinate (G)  at (2,1);
	\coordinate (H)  at (2,0);

	\node at (E) [right]{Set $B$};
	\node at (F) [right]{John};
	\node at (G) [right]{Eric};
	\node at (H) [right]{Sarah};
	\draw (B) -- (G) -- (D) -- (F) -- (C) -- (H) -- (B);
	\end{tikzpicture}
				</latex-image>
			</image>
    </statement>
  </example>

  <example>
    <statement>
      <p>
        Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> both be the set of integers from 1 to 10, and define the relation by <m>a R b</m> means that <m>a</m> evenly divides into <m>b</m>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Here <m>2 R 4</m> since 2 divides into 4 evenly. Similarly <m>5 R 5</m> since it divides into itself. <m>6 \not R 3</m> since 6 doesn't divide into 3.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p> Draw a graphical representation of the divides relation as we did in the sibling example, listing elements of the two sets and drawing lines from the left set to the right where the line means <m>a</m> divides evenly into <m>b</m>.  
          </p>
        </li>
        <li> 
          <p>
            Now list all ordered pairs in the relation.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </statement>
  </example>

  <example>
    <statement>
      <p>
        Let <m>R</m> be the relation from <m>\N</m> to <m>\N</m> where we say <m>a R b</m> if <m>a^2 = b</m>. List the first few ordered pairs of the relation for <m>a = 0, 1, 2, \dots 5</m>.
      </p>
    </statement>
  </example>





 

</section>
